National University Extension Association (NUEA) Records
National University Extension Association (NUEA) Records
1924-1972
National University Extension Association
37.5 linear ft.
The National University Extension Association was founded in 1915. Membership consists of universities and colleges engaged in university extension. The Association’s purpose is to develop and advance ideals, methods, and standards in continuing education and university extension. Its activities include a national annual conference and a number of publications. Records include Board of Directors’ correspondence and meetings, minutes and reports; committee files; correspondence; Project Head Start (U.S.) papers and manuals; Job Corps Driver Education Training papers; papers and photographs of the Office of Education, Adult Basic Education Teacher Trainer Institutes; and subject files for various adult education organizations and divisions. Correspondents whose letters are of greatest depth and duration include those of: Alexander N. Charters, James R.D. Eddy, A.A. Liveright, Ernest Edward McMahon, Julius M. Nolte, Lloyd W. Schram, Paul H. Sheats, and Thurman White. Subject files include those of the Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults and the Division of Correspondence.
149353
Biographical History
The National University Extension Association (NUEA), founded in 1915 and composed of universities and colleges (mostly state universities) engaged in extension programs, has as its purpose the development and advancement of ideals, methods, and standards in continuing education and extension. Its activities include a national annual conference, divisions organized by concerns, and publications. Its regular publications are Guide to Correspondence Study in Colleges and Universities (biannual), NUEA Newsletter (biweekly), Proceedings of annual meetings, The Spectator (bimonthly), and Programs and Registrations (annually, published jointly with the AUEC).
In 1980, the National University Extension Association changed its name to the National University Continuing and Adult Education Association (NUCEA) and then in 1998 to University Continuing and Adult Education Association (UCEA).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The National University Extension Association (NUEA) Records consist of two separate accessions which have not been integrated. The researcher is advised to review both sections to ensure locating all relevant information.
NUEA Records, Part 1
Part 1 of the NUEA records is divided into five series. Board of Directors (3 boxes) contains correspondence of the Secretaries of the Association, reports sent and received by them, and transcripts of the meetings of the Board of Directors and the Executive Committee. Committee files (4 boxes) relate to all the committees created over a forty-year period by the Association. General Correspondence files (12 boxes), 1930-1968, contain both incoming and outgoing letters, arranged chronologically, on a wide variety of subjects. There is also a small subject file of correspondence that concerns annual meetings and new members. NUEA Subject files (7 boxes) are arranged alphabetically by types of financial records and conference, division, or project names.
Project Head Start materials (14 boxes), 1965-1966, are detailed records in fifteen boxes of the special project funded by the Office of Education and directed by an office set up by the Association at the University of Maryland in the summer of 1963. There are university contracts, correspondence, university orientation and training program materials, financial reports, required evaluation reports on the success or failure of the project at each of the participating universities, and general material relating to the program -- its development, progress, and completion. The computer analyses, documenting the completed report, are in two large cartons. Details appear in the shelf list.
There are also two boxes of Oversize material.
NUEA Records, Part 2
Part 2 of the NUEA Records supplements the first accession and includes additional general records and manuals on Project Head Start, and some files on the Job Corps Driver Education Training program. The bulk of materials, including the photographs, are of the federally funded Teacher Trainer Institutes, administered for the U.S. Office of Education by the NUEA, and held in various colleges and universities around the country.
This accession is divided into four series. General records (3 boxes) comprises correspondence, memoranda and reports; there are also numerous lists of participants, professional resources and materials. U.S. Office of Education, Adult Basic Education, Teacher Trainer Institutes (22 boxes) (abbreviated at USOE-ABE-TTI) material is filed by year and within each year, material is filed alphabetically. For 1966 and 1967 there are two subdivisions: general records and those of specific regional institutes. Manuals and Published Materials (4 boxes) contains published material on Project Head Start and other topics. Photographs consists of three boxes of photographs from the USOE-ABE-TTI; many are labelled.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing of all adult education collections. In particular, see the records of NUEA's successor organization, the National University Continuing and Adult Education Association (NUCEA).
The following may also be of interest:
Association of University Evening Colleges (AUEC) Records
Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA) Records
Coalition of Adult Education Organizations (CAEO) Records
Fund for Adult Education (FAE) Records
Galaxy Conference of Adult Education Organizations
Alexander A. Liveright Papers
Paul Sheats Papers
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Charters, Alexander N.; Eddy, James R. D.; Liveright, A. A. (Alexander Albert), 1907-; McMahon, Ernest Edward; Nolte, Julius M. (Julius Mosher), 1894-1964.; Project Head Start (U.S.); Schram, Lloyd W.; Sheats, Paul H., 1907-1984.; White, Thurman J.; Adult Basic Education Teacher Trainer Institutes (U.S.); Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults.; National University Continuing Education Association (U.S.); National University Extension Association -- Archives.; National University Extension Association. -- Division of Correspondence Study.; Adult education.; Federal aid to child development.; Teachers, Training of.; University extension -- United States.; Bibliographies.; Contracts.; Correspondence.; Lists.; Manuals (instructional materials); Memorandums.; Minutes (administrative records); Photographs.; Reports.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the National University Extension Association.
Inventory
- Part 1
  - Board of Directors
    - Correspondence and meetings, 1931-1960 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence and meetings, 1961-1968; undated (Box 2)
    - Minutes and reports, 1955-1960 (Box 3)
  - Committee files
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Time and Place, 1959-1962 (Box 3)
    - Advisory Committee of Universities for Civil Defense, 1962-1963 (Box 3)
    - Committee for Cooperation with the Land Grant Council, 1951-1965 (Box 3)
    - Committee for Cooperation with the National Rehabilitation Association, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Accreditation, ca. 1947 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Awards and Honors, 1957-1966 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Business Affairs, 1957-1964 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Canada-U.S. Relationships, 1953-1961 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Constitutional Revision, Organization Structure and Fee Modification, 1965 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Cooperation with the American Vocational Association, 1958-1961 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Cooperation with Trade and Professional Associations, 1956-1960 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Directors, Constitution, and Fees, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Discussion and Debate Materials, 1951-1965 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Extension Services for the Armed Forces, 1956-1964 (Box 3)
    - Committee on Federal Aid, 1940-1945 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Governmental Relations, 1946-1965; 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Committee on Governmental Relations, Reports and Testimony, 1965 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Grants and Relations with Foundations, 1954-1955 (Box 4)
    - Committee on the Humanities, 1956-1965 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Implications of Atomic Energy, 1950-1964 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Industrial Relations Workers Education, 1955 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Labor Management Relations, 1956-1961 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Liaison with the General Federation of Women's Clubs, 1963-1965 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Liberal Education, 1957-1961 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Organizational Problems, undated (Box 4)
    - Committee on Policies and Membership, 1947-1965 (Box 4)
    - Committee on Political Platforms, 1960 (Box 4)
    - Committee on the Preparation of Extension Leaders, 1950-1952 (Box 5)
    - Committee on Professional Development, 1962-1964 (Box 5)
    - Committee on Publications and Public Information, 1956-1965 (Box 5)
    - Committee on Research, 1947-1965 (Box 5)
    - Committee on Resolutions, 1959-1964 (Box 5)
    - Committee on the Standardization of Extension Credit Courses, 1924 (Box 5)
    - Committee on Technical Institutes, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Committee on Terminal Programs, 1957-1963 (Box 5)
    - Committee on Uniform Statistics, 1932 (Box 5)
    - Committee on UNESCO, 1951-1958 (Box 5)
    - Committee on the Workers Education Movement, 1924 (Box 5)
    - Committee on World Affairs, 1956-1964 (Box 5)
    - Editorial and Publications Committee, 1955 (Box 5)
    - Joint Committee for the Study of Adult Education, undated (Box 5)
    - Policies, Principles, and Practices, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Joint Committee of the AAAE and NEA, 1949 (Box 5)
    - Joint NUEA-AUCC Committee on Uniform Reporting, 1956-1965 (Box 5)
    - National Committee on Publicity, 1941 (Box 6)
    - Position Paper Committee, 1961 (Box 6)
    - Research Committee on Extension and Adult Education, 1950-1966 (Box 6)
    - Reports and Business Practices, 1950-1963; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous, 1956-1964 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence
    - General
      - 1930-1932 (Box 6)
      - Jan 1934 - Sep 1950 (Box 7)
      - Oct 1950 - Sep 1952 (Box 8)
      - Oct 1952 - Dec 1954 (Box 9)
      - 1955 (Box 10)
      - 1956-1957 (Box 11)
      - Jan 1958 - Jun 1960 (Box 12)
      - Jul 1960 - Jun 1962 (Box 13)
      - Jul 1962 - Aug 1963 (Box 14)
      - Sep 1963 - Dec 1964 (Box 15)
      - 1965-1967 (Box 16)
      - 1968 (Box 17)
    - Subject files
      - Annual general meetings, 1959-1966; 5 folders (Box 17)
      - New members, 1953-1965 (Box 17)
  - Project Head Start
    - Contracts, 1965
      - A-M (Box 18)
      - N-Z, Miscellaneous (Box 19)
    - Correspondence
      - General
        - Mar 1965 - Aug 1965 (Box 20)
        - Sep 1965 - Dec 1966 (Box 21)
      - Samples of form letters, 1965 (Box 21)
      - Universities, 1965
        - A-M (Box 21)
        - N-Y (Box 22)
      - Financial reports, 1965
        - A-C (Box 22)
        - D-N (Box 23)
        - O-Z (Box 24)
      - Orientation and training programs, 1965
        - A-K (Box 25)
        - L-S (Box 26)
        - T-Wh (Box 27)
      - Participating institution evaluation reports, 1965
        - A-J (Box 27)
        - K-W (Box 28)
    - Subject files
      - Addressograph plates, 1965 (Box 29)
      - Adult Basic Education Project, 1965 (Box 29)
      - Conference for Participating Institutions, 1965 (Box 29)
      - Directives and forms, 1965 (Box 29)
      - Insurance coverage, correspondence, 1965 (Box 29)
      - Inter-American University Trainees' Personal Data, 1965; 2 folders (Box 29)
      - Management Center reports, 1965 (Box 29)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1965 (Box 29)
      - Photographs
        - General, 1965 (Box 29)
        - Fort Hays and Kansas State College, 1965 (Box 29)
        - Pennsylvania State College, 1965 (Box 29)
        - Rochester Institute of Technology, 1965 (Box 29)
      - Position papers, 1960-1961 (Box 30)
      - Preliminary meetings, planning, Mar-Apr 1965 (Box 30)
      - Program and training manuals, 1965
      - Program Proposal, 1965-1966 (Box 30)
      - Pupil personnel research, University of Texas, 1965 (Box 30)
      - Purchase order clauses, photostats, 1965 (Box 30)
      - Report of the staff training program, typescript, 1965 (Box 30)
      - Request for trainees by university, 1965 (Box 30)
      - Telegrams, 1965 (Box 30)
      - Trainees, by University, 1965 (Box 31)
      - Trainee capacity by University, 2 notebooks (Box 31)
      - United States Government income tax papers, 1965 (Box 31)
      - University evaluation, forms for use in, 1965 (Box 31)
      - Training Assignments, 1965
        - Alabama, Alaska, Arizona, Arkansas (Box 32)
        - California, Colorado, Connecticut (Box 32)
        - Delaware, District of Columbia (Box 32)
        - Florida (Box 32)
        - Georgia (Box 32)
        - Hawaii (Box 32)
        - Idaho, Illinois, Indiana, Iowa (Box 32)
        - Kansas, Kentucky (Box 32)
        - Louisiana (Box 32)
        - Maine, Maryland, Massachusetts, Michigan (Box 32)
        - Minnesota, Missouri, Montana (Box 32)
        - Nebraska, Nevada, New Hampshire, New Jersey, New Mexico (Box 32)
        - New York, North Carolina, North Dakota (Box 32)
        - Ohio, Oklahoma, Oregon (Box 32)
        - Pennsylvania, Puerto Rico (Box 32)
        - Rhode Island (Box 32)
        - South Carolina, South Dakota (Box 32)
        - Tennessee, Texas (Box 32)
        - Utah (Box 32)
        - Vermont, Virginia (Box 32)
        - Washington, West Virginia, Wisconsin, Wyoming (Box 32)
  - Oversized material (Box 33, 34)
  - Subject files
    - Adult Education Association, 1953-1958 (Box 35)
    - Advisory Council of Presidents, 1959 (Box 35)
    - American Association of Collegiate Registrars and Admissions Officers, 1961-1964 (Box 35)
    - American Council on Education, reports, 1952-1956 (Box 35)
    - American Council on Education, 1960-1964 (Box 35)
    - Association for Higher Education, 1963-1964 (Box 35)
    - Canadian Association for Adult Education, 1962 (Box 35)
    - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults
      - 1955-1956 (Box 35)
      - 1957-1965 (Box 36)
    - Conference on Education and the States, 1965 (Box 36)
    - Constitution, NUEA, 1958 (Box 36)
    - Council of National Organizations (AEA), 1955 (Box 36)
    - Division of Audio-Visual Communications, 1931-1965 (Box 36)
    - Division of Community Development, 1957-1966 (Box 36)
    - Division of Conferences and Institutes, 1956-1964 (Box 36)
    - Division of Correspondence Study, 1931-1966 (Box 37)
    - Division of Correspondence Study, reports
      - 1958-1962 (Box 37)
      - 1963-1966 (Box 38)
    - Division of Evening Colleges and Class Extension, 1955-1965 (Box 38)
    - Film Council of America, 1950 (Box 38)
    - Financial record books, 1925-1945 (Box 38)
    - Financial reports, 1951-1965 (Box 38)
    - Fund for Adult Education, 1951-1954 (Box 39)
    - Inter-American Seminar of Overall Planning for Education, 1958 (Box 39)
    - Internal reports, 1966-1968 (Box 39)
    - Joint Commission for the Study of Adult Education, 1949 (Box 39)
    - Mid-Century White House Conference on Children and Youth, 1950 (Box 39)
    - Mid-West Regional Workshop, 1960 (Box 39)
    - National Commission on Accrediting, 1960-1963 (Box 39)
    - National Study of University Extension, 1952 (Box 39)
    - Placement Service
      - Correspondence, 1960-1964 (Box 39)
      - Personal History Records
        - A-E, 1964 (Box 39)
        - F-Z, 1964 (Box 40)
        - A-Z, 1965-1966 (Box 40)
    - Sagamore Conference, 1960 (Box 41)
    - Salary survey and personnel placement correspondence, undated (Box 41)
    - Speeches and reports, miscellaneous, 1924-1965 (Box 41)
    - Survey of Industries on Manpower and Training Needs, 1951 (Box 41)
    - White House Conference on Aging, 1961 (Box 41)
- Part 2
  - General records
    - General business
      - Administrative Manual, 1966 (Box 42)
      - Administrative Manual, Revised 1967 By-Laws, undated (Box 42)
      - Charter, undated (Box 42)
      - Constitution, undated (Box 42)
      - Correspondence, 1965 (Box 42)
      - Directory, 1955 (Box 42)
      - Financial Statements, 1963 (Box 42)
      - Handbook, March 1966 (Box 42)
      - Lists -- Directors, Divisions, Committees, Delegates and Special Appointees, 1956-1957 (Box 42)
      - Member Institutions' List -- Deans and Directors, April 1960 (Box 42)
      - Meetings (chron.)
        - Board of Directors, 1957 (Box 42)
        - 45th Annual Meeting, 1960; Business Meeting, report; Deans and Directors, report (Box 42)
        - Regional Meeting, Discussion Groups, 1961 (Box 42)
        - 49th Annual Meeting, 1964; President Neville's remarks, rosters, speeches (Box 42)
        - Annual Meeting, General Session #1, "Future of Higher Education", 1971 (Box 42)
      - Personnel -- Applications, 1962-1967 (Box 42)
    - Committees
      - Arts
        - Minutes, 1950 (Box 42)
        - Memoranda, Arts in Society, 1959 (Box 42)
        - Statistics, 1961 (Box 42)
      - Conferences and Institutes, Subcommittee on Procedures, Report--Survey of Conference and Short Course Procedures, 1955 (Box 42)
      - Discussion and Debate, Materials and Interstate Cooperation, Annual Report, 1955-1957 (Box 42)
      - Governmental Relations, Report, 1958 (Box 42)
      - Humanities Committee
        - Meeting, 1962 (Box 42)
        - Liberal Education Memoranda, 1958-1961 (Box 42)
        - Minutes, Agendas, Notes, 1957 (Box 42)
        - Minutes, Reports, Memoranda, Misc., 1957-1958 (Box 42)
        - Reports, 1957-1959 (Box 42)
      - Policy Statement Committee, 1961 (Box 42)
      - Radio-Television, Audio-Visual Committee, 1953-1954; 1957-1959 (Box 42)
      - Reports and Business Practices, Annual Statistical Report, 1958 (Box 42)
      - Reports, 1953-1958 (Box 43)
      - Research
        - Criteria, 1958 (Box 43)
        - Minutes, 1958-1959 (Box 43)
        - Misc., 1959 (Box 43)
        - Proposed Functions, 1958 (Box 43)
        - Report, 1952-1953 (Box 43)
      - Research Subcommittee
        - Annual Report, 1958-1959 (Box 43)
        - Meeting Minutes, 1958 (Box 43)
      - View of the Future, report, 1972 (Box 43)
      - World Affairs, 1960; programs, propositJons, misc., conference acceptances (Box 43)
    - Divisions
      - Audio-Visual Communication, Membership Directory, 1957 (Box 43)
      - Community Development
        - Meeting program, 1959 (Box 43)
        - Report, Community Development in University Extension, 1956 (Box 43)
        - Seminar, information and registration forms, 1960 (Box 43)
        - Third NUEA Community Development Seminar, Proceedings, 1963 (Box 43)
      - Conferences and institutes, minutes, 1966 (Box 43)
      - Evening Colleges and Class Extension
        - Annual Reports, 1956-1958 (Box 43)
        - Memorandum -- membership lists, 1958 (Box 43)
        - Program, 1959 (Box 43)
    - Conferences (chron.)
      - Official Convention Roster, 1958 (Box 43)
      - Northwest Regional University Extension Conf., list of delegates, 1959 (Box 43)
      - 45th Annual Conference, agenda, 1960 (Box 43)
      - Regional Conference, roster, 1961 (Box 43)
      - 46th Annual Conference, 1961; resolutions (business session) roster (Box 43)
      - Wingspread Arts Conference, report, 1962 (Box 43)
      - National ABE Conference, participant replies, 1968 (Box 43)
      - National Leadership Conference, logistics, 1968 (Box 43)
    - Project Head Start
      - Office of Economic Opportunity, 1964-1967 (Box 43)
      - Dr. Robert Pitchell, folder, 1965 (Box 43)
      - Proposals, 1966-1967 (Box 43)
      - Proposal, 1968 (Box 44)
      - Staff Report on Conference for Participating Institutions, Teacher Training, 1965 (Box 44)
    - Job Corps Driver Education Training
      - Colorado State University, 1968 (Box 44)
      - Eastern New Mexico University, 1968 (Box 44)
      - Job Corps Driver Education, 1968-1969 (Box 44)
      - Oregon State Board of Higher Education, 1968 (Box 44)
      - Original Proposal, 1968 (Box 44)
      - Portland State, 1968-1969 (Box 44)
      - Training -- Contract, 1968 (Box 44)
      - University of Illinois, 1968 (Box 44)
      - University of Pittsburgh, 1968 (Box 44)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Comments -- Community Organization Programs in University Extension, 1955 (Box 44)
      - History -- University Extension Legislation, 1957 (Box 44)
      - Proposals
        - Concentrated Employment Program -- Scheur Amendment, 1967 (Box 44)
        - Specialist Services and Technical Assistance, OEO, undated (Box 44)
      - Recommendations and analysis and interpretation, "The University's Responsibility for the General Education of Adults", 1955 (Box 44)
      - Report -- Continuation Centers, 1954 (Box 44)
      - Statistics -- Correspondence or Home Study, 1956-1957 (Box 44)
      - Tentative Roster -- Workshop on the Arts, 1958 (Box 44)
  - U.S. Office of Education, Adult Basic Education, Teacher Training Institute
    - 1965
      - Administration, 1965-1966 (Box 45)
      - Florida State University, 1965 (Box 45)
      - Nichols, Herb, 1965-1967 (Box 45)
    - 1966
      - ABE Institutes, General (Box 45)
      - ABE Report -- Reference Materials (Box 45)
      - Advisory Council (Box 45)
      - Basic Analog Model of Systems Analysis and Evaluation (Box 45)
      - Biographical Data Sheet (Box 45)
      - Conferences -- ABE Conference, Mayflower Hotel (Box 45)
      - Consultant List (Box 45)
      - Core Curriculum (Box 46)
      - Curriculum Guide and Background Statements (Box 46)
      - Data Analysis and Evaluation Design (Box 46)
      - Directory (Box 46)
      - Educational Technology (2) (Box 46)
      - Evaluation
        - Design (Box 46)
        - Forms (3) (Box 46)
        - Forms, Regional Reports, Educational Psychology Associates (Box 46)
        - Meetings (Box 46)
        - Report (Box 46)
        - Report (Abstract of) (Box 46)
      - "Documents Relating to the USOE ABE Teacher Trainer Institutes" (Box 46)
      - Final Report -- Summer ABE Institutes (Box 46)
      - Finance (Box 46)
      - General Correspondence, Memos (Box 46)
      - General Correspondence (A-H) (Box 47)
      - Grant (Box 47)
      - Information and Materials List (Box 47)
      - Joint Staff Meeting, USOE/ NUEA (Box 47)
      - Manual of Training Materials (Box 47)
      - Materials to T.T.I. Directors (4) (Box 47)
      - National Advisory Council (Box 47)
      - National Association of Public School Adult Educators (NAPSAE) (Box 47)
      - New Careers Training Program (Box 48)
      - Participants (2) (Box 48)
      - Progress Reports First Second (Box 48)
      - Proposed Weekly Schedule for Different Regions Schedule (Box 48)
      - "Summer 1966 Teacher Trainer Institutes" -- draft (Box 48)
      - U.S. Office of Education (USOE) -- Correspondence (Box 48)
      - USOE Mission (Box 48)
    - 1966 Regional Institues
      - Florida State University (2) (Box 48)
      - North Carolina State University (Box 48)
      - State University of New York (SUNY) at Buffalo (2) (Box 48)
      - SUNY Buffalo, Appendix to Final Report (Box 48)
      - SUNY Buffalo, Supplemental Report (Box 49)
      - University of California at Los Angeles (UCLA) (2) (Box 49)
      - University of Colorado (Box 49)
      - University of Connecticut (Box 49)